A Guide to the Papers of James McDowell 1752 (1800-1878)
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James McDowell 1752 (1800-1878)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1707, 1755
This collection consists of ca. 600 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
This collection of ca. 600 items consists largely of the papers of Colonel James McDowell of Rockbridge County, Virginia, for the years 1752 (1800-1878). McDowell was the father of James McDowell (1795-1851) governor of Virginia from 1843-1846, and Mrs. Thomas Hart Benton and was a man of some political and financial importance as well as a colonel in the militia.
The coming of the War of 1812 and Rockbridge County's attitude toward the war are among other subjects mentioned. Land speculation in Kentucky and North Carolina, in which McDowell seems to have been deeply interested, is the subject of many letters. McDowell gave his son, James, 3,000 acres of Kentucky land at his marriage. The Federalists in this area and their political possibilities are mentioned.
The question of the location of the University of Virginia is mentioned in a letter of 1818, with geographical statistics to prove that Lexington was really the center of the state and that the University should be located there. There are also several letters discussing the finances of Washington College (Lexington, Virginia; now Washington and Lee University).
There are a number of letters to Colonel McDowell from such men as: Sam Houston, Richard Bland Lee, James Barbour, John Floyd, Thomas Ritchie, Francis Smith, and other Virginia politicians. There is an interesting letter from C.M. Conrad, Secretary of War to Congressman John Letcher dated in 1852. There are also several good political letters mentioning John Calhoun, Henry Clay, Andrew Jackson, and local Virginia politicians.
Arrangement
This collection has been placed in chronogical order, although separate folders for the two accessions have been retained.
Contents List
- Indenture between Thomas and Jane Williams and James Greenlee of Augusta County, Va. 1752 Aug. 19 (Box 1)
- Will of John Linton of Orangeburgh, Va. 1791 Jan. 13 (Box 1)
- James Wood to James McDowell 1797 Sept. 20, ALS (Box 1)
- John Breckinridge to James McDowell 1792 July 30, ALS (Box 1)
- Gamble and Temple to James McDowell 1795 April 6, ALS (Box 1)
- Affadavit of John Mason re: election procedures 1800 Nov. 15 (Box 1)
- Business, Political, and Religious Correspondence of James McDowell 1801 March-Dec. (Box 1)
- Correspondence of James McDowell 1803 Feb.-Dec. (Box 1)
- Andrew Morrison to James McDowell 1804 April 4, ALS (Box 1)
- Correspondence of James McDowell 1805 Jan.-Oct. (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Business Papers of James McDowell 1806 March-Dec. (Box 1)
- Legal Papers 1806 Sept. 26 (Box 1)
- Letters of William H. Cabell, Richard Bland Lee, and Sam Houston to James McDowell 1806-1807 (Box 1)
- Business and Political Correspondence of James McDowell 1807 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Business Papers of James McDowell 1808 (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence 1809 April-Nov. (Box 1)
- Business Correspondence 1809-1810 (Box 1)
- Political and Business Correspondence 1810 Feb.-Nov. (Box 1)
- Business Letters 1811 Aug.-Oct. (Box 1)
- Letters of Allen Trimble, J.W. Pleasants, John Carr, W.P. Anderson, and J. Barbour to James McDowell 1811 (Box 1)
- Political and Military Correspondence 1812 March-Nov. (Box 1)
- Legal, Military, and Political Correspondence and Papers 1813 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Account of James Young; List of Negroes of estate of Alexander McNutt 1813-1819 (Box 1)
- Military and Political Correspondence 1814 March-Dec. (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Military Papers 1815 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1816 Feb.-Nov. (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Business and Political Papers 1817 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1818 Jan.-Oct. (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1819-1820, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Letters of J.H. Benton, John Floyd, Thomas Ritchie, and Francis Smith to James McDowell 1821 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1821-1822 Jan.-Nov. (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1823 Jan. & Dec. (Box 2)
- Alexander McNutt to Peter Salling, Jr. 1823 Sept. 14, ALS (Box 2)
- William S. Rutherford to James and David Greenlee 1824 April 7, ALS (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1823 Jan., Feb. and Sept. (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1825 (Box 2)
- Business Letters and Receipts 1826 (Box 2)
- W.C. Rives to Henry Harris 1826 July 11, ALS (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1827 Jan., Feb. (Box 2)
- John [Pusinger?] to Andrew Fudge 1828 Jan. 23, ALS (Box 2)
- Business and Legal Correspondence including Ballard Smith, John Pusinger, Robert White 1829 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1830 (Box 2)
- Thomas Hart Benton and Jesse Benton Freemont to [Sarah Preston McDowell] ca. 1830-1832, ALS (Box 2)
- Joseph Cabell to William Massie; Receipts 1830-1834, ALS (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1831 Feb.-Dec. (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1832 June-Oct. (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1833 Jan.-Sept. (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Business and Legal Papers 1834 Feb.-Sept. (Box 2)
- Business and Legal Correspondence and Papers 1834-1835 (Box 2)
- Business and Personal Correspondence 1835 Jan.-Nov. (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1836 Jan.-Sept. (Box 2)
- Indenture between Elizabeth and Robert McDowell and Rebecca (McDowell) Lewis of Lexington, Va. 1837 Jan. 4 (Box 2)
- Family and Business Correspondence 1837 Jan.-Sept. (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1838 Jan.-Nov. (Box 2)
- Receipt 1838 Dec. 18 (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1839 May-Oct. (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1840 March-Sept. (Box 2)
- Business Papers 1841 (Box 2)
- Personal and Legal Correspondence 1843 (Box 2)
- Account of Mayo Cabell 1843, 1844, 1845 (Box 2)
- Receipt; John Letcher to James McDowell 1844 Jan. 18, 1844 April 9, ALS (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1844 April-Dec. (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Military Papers 1846 (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence 1847 Jan.-Oct. (Box 2)
- Political and Business Correspondence 1847 Jan.-Oct. (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1848 Jan.-Oct. (Box 2)
- Personal and Legal Correspondence including C.R. Harris, A.C. Baine, Robert G. Scott 1849 (Box 2)
- Business and Political Letters, Thomas J. Michie and James D. Watts 1851 Feb. 25 (Box 2)
- William White to William [Luchess?] 1851 Feb. 25, ALS (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1851 April & Nov. (Box 2)
- Personal and Business Correspondence 1852 Jan.-Sept. (Box 2)
- Stock certificate 1852 Jan. 1 (Box 2)
- James McDowell to H.E. Morgan 1852 Aug. 12 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of C.M. Conrad (Sec. of War), C.C. Baldwin, and Wm. R. Winn and papers of Gov. McDowell's slaves. 1852-1856 (Box 2)
- Personal and Business Correspondence 1853 Jan.-July (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1854 (Box 2)
- Notebook including notes for a speech (by James McDowell in support of Henry Wise for Governor) ca. 1855 (Box 2)
- Personal and Business Correspondence 1855 April-Sept. (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Legal and Business Papers 1856 Feb.-March (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1857 Oct. (Box 2)
- Legal and Business Correspondence and Papers 1858 Jan.-Sept. (Box 2)
- Political and Personal Correspondence 1858-1868 (Box 2)
- Personal and Business Letters 1859 May- Sept. (Box 2)
- Personal and Business Letters 1860 Apr.-Dec. (Box 2)
- Thomas Martin to Brigadier General Anderson 1862 May, ALS (Box 2)
- Ham Webb to D.A. McLaurin 1864 June [24?], ALS (Box 2)
- Broadside of General Early to protect sodier families' supplies 1864 Nov. 12 (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1865 Jan.-Oct. (Box 2)
- J.M. Cary to Mrs. Norris [1866], ALS (Box 2)
- Correspondence including W.H. Smith, Wm. [Mahone?], Jed Hotchkiss, Lee Memorial Association, Alex Brown 1869-1878 (Box 2)
- Business and Military Correspondence and Papers including Thomas Preston n.d., April, Nov. (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Legal and Military Papers n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence n.d. (Box 2)